yeah good to see you
yeah um it's it's been i think the last
time we saw each other
the what was then still called reporting
3.0
yeah that was in amsterdam i believe
near the schiphol
airport yeah yeah um
so we just had a little warm-up
conversation before
we started the recording and and you you
said that um
you've been um in thailand for since
since the lockdown started
um yes i came here um march
15 two days before the closing of the
airports in brussels
and you know i didn't want to be
separated from my family so i hurried to
come here
had a two weeks guaranteeing and then
yeah i've been here
living in lockdown uh for a while
but you know the death rate here is 200
times lesser than in europe so it's
it's uh yeah it's not that bad as you
can imagine and
people now go out again but we have
masks yeah
i mean it's fascinating how um in all
asian countries
there's not not much of an issue around
mosques and i mean anybody who's
traveled in asia
knows that it's normal for asian people
when they have a little flu or they
feel bad in the morning they get the
mask out and they
go out with the mask because they have
the social responsibility to say
i might be infectious so i'm gonna yeah
exactly you know this theory uh i think
uh she was called ruth benedict um
and she wrote a book long time ago i
think it was in the 30s maybe
where she distinguished shame based from
guild-based cultures
um and so in east asia it's it's a
shame-based culture
and so the the other plays
a very big role so you do things
because of the other right and that has
both negative and positive
uh aspect but so the idea of you know
not being a nuisance to the other
that is very strong here and it's kind
of a natural thing this
i mean i have all these european friends
complaining about you know
having masks and this is just another
debate here it's like
of course if i can save a life you know
by
putting on a mask and protect myself
because this is another thing there's a
certain fear here of
you know hygienic very strong hygienic
uh
ideology so it plays together right the
fear of infection
as well as the the care uh
for the you know the heart the social
harmony right whether it's confusionism
or buddhism they all have this stress on
social harmony
doing everything you can not to upset
the other person like even
you know apparently uh buddhist monks
have these 70 different emotions so they
can recognize
you know so they they people look at
your face and when you
show some unhappiness they they
immediately think oh i did something
wrong so what can i do
to avoid the bad feeling and i i find it
very pleasant personally
yeah no it's living in a culture that
begins by considering the other
um is is quite yeah for us
western as well yeah yeah i have to be
i have to be careful when i go to
belgium not to smile too much
[Laughter]
right i remember i was a scuba diving
instructor on core tower for a while
and um so i i've lived in thailand for
almost a year
and um even just the tone of the voice i
i realized that
that our western sort of bass heavy
booming voices can be quite
harsh on the ear of most ties i i
noticed that i
tried to speak a little higher um
i travel with i travel with my family to
italy and and
you know my wife thought they were
fighting all the time because the way
they speak is
if you don't know how they are it
actually sounds aggressive
you know if you just listen to the sound
the way they
they get excited about stuff even in
normal conversation
a lot of a lot of people say that about
the germans but i think that's a bit
unfair
like that they think that germans are
constantly arguing um
yeah normally in this series of um
conversations
i i start off by by inviting people to
tell a little bit about their own
um story and um i've done a little bit
of
i mean i know some of your story already
but but i did a little bit of background
research and
you spent a lot of time in the when was
it in
in the 1990s or even 80s in in america
working for the information service um
and and then you also you also okay so
yeah
be really interesting to hear the
earlier yeah the story as well
so so in terms of my professional career
i worked nine years for the united
states information agency
uh which uh perhaps elizabeth at the
time
was an arm of the state department uh
but which had to reflect the the
plurality of u.s culture so as was as
the same time kind of transmission bill
for us government
you know positions like you know what
what do the u.s want to do with
xyz but we also had the whole gamut of
magazines from right to left so we had
the nation the new republic the
progressive in these times on the left
we had the national review and the
heritage foundation
and commentary on you know on the right
and everything in between
so that was very pleasant but i actually
did that in brussels
so it was the american library in
brussels i was in charge of doing
uh like synthetic reports for
usually like second level officials in
nato and
shape and the european union and the
belgian ministry of you know so that
basically the people working
for the ministers would then ask us you
know what what is happening in the u.s
around abortion for example
right and at the time there was no
internet so we had access to all these
amazing databases like the congressional
research surveys that you know that were
like really rich
so it was a great job and then it also
makes
makes clear because i've often wondered
how in your curation
of the peer-to-peer foundation website
which by now has what
nine thousand sub pages or something
like that twenty thousand twenty two
thousand
wow and seventy and seventy five million
views uh like a year and a half ago
so so the synthetic brain and the
the library capacity of of um
scanning um yeah i seem to have a
particular type of brain
um like there's a lot of things i can't
do i'm not physical so don't ask me
to repair a bicycle because i
i will destroy it for 30 years you know
even the best expert can repair
after i've come through trying to repair
it
but in terms of like pattern recognition
i i
i really do that well you know it's
maybe embarrassing to say that by
yourself but i i really think that's
true it's in the capacity to
almost visually see patterns and
and then you know the joy of putting
them together
um you know i had i had mystical
experiences like that
two times where i would read something
and because it put so many things that i
couldn't put together
you know in a kind of integral framework
like for
three days i'm literally high because
that does it for me you know like
wow wow like inside
you know yeah yeah so that's the
personality quirk it's
you know it's don't wish it on everybody
but
uh um yeah i'm good at that i resonate
strongly with that because
like what i when i did my my phd
research
i very early on realized that um
academically we're often trained to when
we read a text
to look for the bits where we don't
agree and then make a big statement
about why this person is wrong and and
very early on i decided that that wasn't
what i'm
interested in and i think when you do
synthesis what you're trying to do is to
to find the jewels in in somebody's work
and that like i always say um the stuff
that really shines when you when you
read
somebody's work in a book and sometimes
there's just one paragraph that
that really jumps exactly and you see it
immediately that's
that's what happens to me like you know
i i just it just springs out of the page
like immediately
i don't know how that works exactly and
you know that's why i'm always being
very sympathetic to integral approaches
integrative approaches you know
as ken wilbur says nobody's hundred
percent wrong
right so do you see something
you know we're talking before uh before
we started the recording about the
bruderhof
i'm not a christian uh but i'm
fascinated by
you know how they live together and
something to learn
even from people that you disagree with
and i can't find the same joy in looking
at the radical atheist group
because they they will so a perspective
gives you some
insight it's like you eliminate
something and you also hide some things
with a perspective right
and so the idea of being able to look at
something
through multiple perspectives that for
me
shines more light on the object you're
trying to understand
absolutely and so the commons which is
my perspective
you know shines a particular light on
reality which not
everybody else but then so does the
growth and so there's both capitalism
post growth and you know and
regenerative approaches
each of these approaches highlights some
aspect of
reality for me that relates very
strongly to
this this sort of epistemological aikido
that i tried to do in my book
um with um
taking people closer to the questions
rather than the solutions and the
answers
because of course we need solutions and
answers in a world that's failing on so
many levels for us at the moment
um but but if we actually as
cultures meeting and as a culture um
held the questions centrally yeah then
then you can you can listen to somebody
else's perspective and it's not
quite so important whether you agree
with it or not because it shines a light
onto the question that you have in
common with that person
and if you find the answer if it's about
fighting whose answer and whose solution
is right
then then we can't learn together um
exactly
so that yeah but what moved you from
from working with information in that
way to that
phase where you you did quite a bit of
technology work um
yeah so so from the usia i went to
british petroleum
[Music]
i worked for the agri-business division
and nobody knows that but bp was the
biggest producer of animal feed
in the early 90s
and it was a really interesting job
because
you know i was working for the top layer
like the the 15 top
managers of this division with 25 000
people under them and i was just like
you know under that um
and so i would get like a manager coming
to me and saying oh can you prove to me
that
you know and then the other one would
come and he would
ask me can you prove to me that not
right and so i was obliged to really
put on a perspectival hat to help this
particular director makes his case in
the board
and at the same time i had to put the
other hat of the other guy who wanted to
oppose this project
and you know and that was interesting so
that you really learned these
perspectival
you know relative truths it depends how
you look at it
um and
yeah then after that i did that for
three years
i started a magazine called wave which
was like wired in mono 2000
you know kind of a more counter cultural
version of
why it became uh did that for three
years and then two
startups uh in
tribal marketing uh um
and so we wanted to do ethical marketing
so
like okay you want to have some
influence on a particular group
you know you just don't broadcast you go
talk to the moderators and
and it's okay uh you know what's allowed
in your
in your community how can we help you is
you know so kind of engaging dialogue
about
um of course working for clients you
know i was still doing business at the
time
and then another one doing intranets and
extranets
so creating relationships with suppliers
and clients and
uh that was interesting uh
but then like we got in 2000 the
internet bubble and that was
my second company was like really in
trouble because that we lost 90
of our
[Music]
our clients in three months you know
like was a
good experience um yeah and then my last
job was
what i already knew it would be that i
had a big big burnout in 96
and then i decided to do one last job at
belgacom the largest telecommunications
company at the time in belgium
with a view of leaving business
altogether
so the idea was you know let me
get a well-paying job and then save as
much as i can and then
so i i met my thai wife
and then i ended up doing a two-year
sabbatical
in chiang mai northern thailand where
i'm now
and i i studied phase transitions so i
wanted to know
you know so i had been a marxist when
i'm in my 20s
because okay that's another sideline
story but let me tell you quickly that
one also so i wasn't happy
so when i started understanding that you
know that kind of revolution
wasn't going to happen so then i decided
what if i can change the world i have to
change myself
right so i did you know almost
all the california therapies in
existence you know
uh s seminars uh bioenergy
primal scream you name it you know i've
done them
and then another seven years uh
spiritual search
you know like it happens to other people
in psychology they say well there's more
than that
it's not just about you it's about you
know um
so the eastern stuff the western stuff
you know it was in parallel basically
and so and then when i started doing my
internet companies that was like
okay i've done enough work on myself now
i want to create something in the in the
world
but i discovered that you know just
doing business wasn't my thing
and so hence the sabbatical
and so my question was
you know how do you change the world
right and by looking at the end of the
roman empire the 15th century the 18th
century all these you know big
big changes mostly europe because i'm
european
um i came away with a an understanding
that seed forms are very important
so in other words before you have these
big violent
uprisings you usually have you know
one or two centuries where
because the old system no longer works
people you know go
some kind of exodus right and start
doing things differently
and and then these forms consolidate
from subsystems eventually then
get into a fight and become the new norm
so that's the idea
right and so my conviction second
conviction was that today
these seed forms are the re-emergence of
the commons
that if you leave you know the purely
capitalist dynamics
what you try to do today is almost in
every case some kind of
some form of commoning you know enabled
by these new digital technologies which
allow people to connect
globally uh so it's two billion people
not just connecting and communicating
but self organizing
and creating new value circuits
right so just give you an example maybe
not the best one
but people in austin belgium can order
on facebook sorry
it's facebook but that's what they do
and they order
from a collective of fishermen you know
collective purchasing of organic
healthy fish you know
that's that's a that's a new value
circuit right they
they leave the middlemen behind they
don't go to the store
uh they don't even go to the market they
they make a solidarity-based agreement
with the fishermen
you know like in uh community supported
agriculture this is called community
supported fisheries it's the same thing
right and you know wherever you look
today
you'll find at least two to three
percent of population already engaged in
these new forms right so
nearly all provisioning systems habitat
food transportation are already
morphing to a certain degree into
commons
centric forms
[Music]
and so that's what i'm observing i i
when i started with my wiki which is you
know now 20 000
22 000 articles i said okay it has to be
real
not how things should be but what people
are actually doing to change
and then i look at it how you know how
is it working what's the governance
what's the property
and so slowly then you you cohere some
insights
so that's the second level and
for me it's about being factual and
coherent
so you know new facts you change your
theory
but it has to be coherent right so it's
some people call this low theory because
it doesn't aim to be a theory of
everything
but you are consolidating your insights
you know in one particular domain or
perspective
or and so
my priorities how do we
support extend the place of the commons
in our societies because historically
what we see i think is in history is
this kind of
succession of extractive and
regenerative faces
you know when an extractive regime kind
of overuses and collapses
then the healing period is actually
around regenerating the commons
you've recently written a piece that
that actually
um like this is a common pattern that
has happened in the past yes so i've
looked
so these theories are called wave pulse
theories
so kind of you have a move to one
polarity
then something bad happens and that's
the pulse
that then generates a counter reaction
right
and so when you look at biophysical
economics
when you look at peter turchin and what
he calls it's clio dynamics when you
look at
polany calpolani the double movement you
you really see this recurring
it isn't interesting because because i
like i'm
just doing some work with my colleagues
at h3uni um
this this course that tony hodgson
developed called transformational
learning journeys and yesterday we had a
session
on dilemma navigation and into charles
hampton turner's dilemma navigation is
is also about like if
if if you have two opposing values but
they both have value
and and need to be honored then you're
not in a choice between this
or that and the so many of our problems
actually come from mistaking a
dilemma for a choice and choices are
either or type
um decisions but dilemmas need to be
navigated
a bit like sailing against the wind and
it
it resonates with what you were just
describing yeah yeah i'm so i'm not
familiar with this particular
uh concept but yeah it's that
yeah and then you know if if you know a
bit i'm sure you do
you know about integral approaches it's
you know it's transcend and include
right so it's not just about saying
capital means bad we need something
totally different
it's saying you know we have serious
problem with this system but there's
some good stuff in it
yeah so can we imagine a higher form of
integration
where we can actually for example keep
the efficiency
you know of of private companies
uh but in a higher level system that
doesn't destroy the planet for example
right so i'm never ready to just say
everything that is existing is bad it
needs to be totally replaced which i
think is very very dangerous
because we don't have so many things the
functional equivalence
yet right that's fascinating because
like i just wanted to come back because
you earlier
said in your youth you were a marxist i
wanted to double check on on something
that because
famously marx said about himself that he
is not a ma
i am not a marxist so when when you say
you were a marxist does that mean
you were very interested in the work of
marx
or in the work of the people um who then
call themselves marxist
afterwards because probably probably
more the second because uh you know i
was a trotskyist so then you have this
you know this kind of lineage and of
course it was very limiting
because you know for example
now i'm kind of planning to look into
associationist mutualists distributists
uh forms of the labor movement because
you know the labor movement is about
commons and most people don't know that
but you know
welfare is social commons right so when
you lose
access to your natural resources and
that's what capital did you know it
enclosed
the land privatized it should you know
chase the farmers away
and they became you know works without
means of production
i think that's still very much correct
as an analysis
so they you know what they did then was
to mutualize
their life risk right so when you don't
have natural resource companies you move
to social commerce
so i can see the history of the labor
movement as
uh you know a revival of social comments
but for example when you're in that
perspective
that we just discussed then i knew about
reforms
reformists i knew about anarchists
that's all i knew about
this you know the story we were told
when i was in my 20s
was a very limited story of what
actually had happened in history
you know so i never heard that there
were
you know parties getting 30 percent of
the vote which were neither
marxists neither reformists neither
anarchism was something else
and actually represented this idea of
you know distributed property right
so the commons is not only about
you know a new form of common property
about mutualizing something
but i think in terms of like you know
balance of power we really need also to
protect individual property so it's not
about
you know collectivism it's it's also
about creating
a distribution of power distribution of
property
you know something are better done
together some things are
you know might be you know so we don't
anticipate
uh the difference between my view and
and and
is that i believe value is created
by everyone
and so basically value is created not by
commodifying it by contributions
so every citizen every inhabitant is
productive and creates value
caring is commoning caring is value
creation
so that needs to be recognized once you
recognize that then you have to
recognize that civil society is actually
productive
not just the market right because that's
the view we have now
you can only create value through
extraction
basically right and
regenerative approaches you know which
is what you stand for
you need philanthropy taxation but
there is very little direct furnish
you know finance and capital available
for doing regenerative work it's it's
systemic right it's systemic
because we believe the market creates a
value we need to tax the market value
and then
only then can we give something and
redistribute it
and i think that's completely wrong so
we need to recognize
that everyone creates value and create
what we call
pre-distribution regimes right
and then we seek market forms
that are generative towards the
community and the web of life
so it's not about abolishing the market
it's about
creating a new framework for it where
you know it doesn't
exceed the planetary boundaries which is
a negative way of looking at it
but in a positive way and i think that's
what you bring to the table
you know it's it's being regenerative
it's about not just maintaining it's
about healing
right and then i i talk about the state
because unlike many other people i do
believe we need it i need
i think we need common good institutions
because here's the difference if you're
an anarchist or libertarian
you think the world is constituted
either by individuals creating contracts
with each other
or by groups you know like a federation
of
that was the anarchist point of view the
19th century
and i don't think that's true i think we
always already start
from a society a relationality
um and that even the commons is selfish
like if you do free software enlightened
self-interest
well not just enlightened i i'm more
negative than that you know if you do
free software
it's very good that you do free software
but do you think about ecology probably
not
you know look at blockchain and bitcoin
you know they're
they have strong open source elements
they have strong
ecosystem ecosystemic approaches
but their energy regime
is awful yeah right so that's what i'm
trying to say is that it's not enough
just to do commenting on your own you
need common good institutions that kind
of protect
the common good of everyone living in a
territory
but i'm increasingly thinking about
virtual territories
right and see the world as a kind of
mixing of both territory
and kind of virtual nations that are
involved in flows
like the digital nomads right we have 25
000 of them here
uh before kovit uh you know they have
their own economy they move around they
go to medellin they go to tenerife they
go to ubud
at the moment it's more they went
because um they went oh yes yes
we don't know how that evolves yeah yeah
we don't know how that's going to go
it's true
but but pretty briefly there's so many
places where we could go
go and you've already said so many
things that i would like to pick up on
um just naming three and then you can
choose
which which one you pick up um
this conversation that we have about um
this is the end of capitalism we need to
need to find a new system or is there a
way like what i heard through
and what you were saying is that there
might be a way to redesign
capitalism to a point where it won't be
what we now call capitalism anymore
and so in that sense the people who say
no we might need to undo capitalism
um we'll also get that bit because it
will transform so fundamentally but but
honoring the the value and the useful
things that are still in it so
because i i find this this radical sort
of
rather than redesign um stop and start
again with something else
um which creates such a
backlash from the system that
that's a very good question i i have
some ideas about this so one is this
idea that
you can create uh create new frameworks
around the existing
right so i'm particularly fond of for
example the
economy economy for the common good so
this is christian felber
uh and his uh you know in the movement
so he looked at all the european
constitutions and
he said okay every single constitution
says the economy should serve the common
good
it there's no constitution that says the
economy should serve private
shareholders it's it's the reality but
it's not in the constitution
and then he says the common good
is not metaphysical it's something that
we can democratically agree on through a
democratic process
right and so you know ten thousand
members two thousand organizations
are trying it out they came up with this
kind of double uh
accounting framework one for regions and
one for corporations
17 clusters of impact
right and you put them outside you see
for example the government could say you
know we do an investment policy and we
will
use this impact as criteria for
investment
so if you do good you get
more subsidies in this taxation if you
do bad impacts
you pay more taxation you get less
subsidies you know something of that
order right
so what you're doing there is like
outside in change you still have
corporations
you sit at the cio but they have to
behave differently
in order to get ahead so i think that's
a very interesting approach
uh because this is a dilemma if you're
if you're an anti-capitalist right
the thing is are you really sure that
within 10 years
you can change the system i don't think
so
so it's like a marriage can't live with
them can't live without them
you know you you have to to deal with
what you have
and you know get to mutually beneficial
you know compromise that works for
everyone
so that's how i see how we should deal
with these issues it's not from saying
one
one day from the other like let's
abolish everything
it's you know how can we frame things in
a way that
the whole incentive regime you know
pushes people to behave differently i i
think that makes a lot of sense
um but what i've noticed
in in our kind of
movement and our like that the people we
we connect with
um is that very often so many of the
good examples i mean you mentioned
the um community supported fisheries
do make creative use of uh
information technology and and and high
technology
and we're talking through computers at
the moment um
in order to create these new more
commons oriented peer-to-peer structures
but then part of the
the future say is like even since the
beginning of
like like um since limits to growth just
recently had a conversation with dennis
meadows and he kind of
almost kind of washed my head a little
bit on on
um being like i would have never called
myself a techno optimist before and i
don't consider myself that but but he
was
actually quite strong on um
when i asked him how he sees the future
it was very much
more people on the land again much more
localized uh living with a in
a much lower energy regime and
so people people being directly involved
in primary production again farming
and biomaterials production and
reforestation
and all those kind of things and um
and so it keeps this looming question of
when we build all these infrastructures
with the commons engine and with
holochain and with
and and and we build networks that like
we talked earlier how
it's easy these days when you do this um
movement building and connecting and
integration work
that you end up being global have lots
of
amazing friends all over the globe and
involved in conversations in costa rica
and in
argentina and in spain and in germany
and in belgium wherever
but you if you don't watch out you can
lose a little bit the local connection
of of
um what you're actually doing in your
community and and my concern at the
moment is a little bit how
how do we ensure that we actually also
build the analog equivalents
um because we might just
no i think you're completely right and
so we talk about cosmo local right so
the idea of cosmo local
is everything that's light
is shared globally
and everything that's heavy is on
locally so what we mean by that is that
knowledge should not be restricted to
intellectual property
you i think it's very useful to have a
community of farmers in nepal
to discuss with the community of farmers
in
in the andes because their bio
whatever you call it i'm not sure how to
call it but you know the and the
the biome the the biome can be very very
similar and there's a lot they can learn
and there is a there's a case to be made
that knowledge share knowledge is very
important for example you look at the
inca
empire you know and it really goes up
and down
and so without the incas
the food production would go down by 90
so massive die outs of the local
populations
uh because they just you know they just
regressed to their like what they really
know
on their own and so then you have very
low populations
uh while when the inca empire then you
know grew again
then you see the population levels go up
so that's the importance of having
shared knowledge base which you know
adds on to your
own and uh you know you look at the
middle ages in europe you know the tru
the travelers were very important like
the guilds
were organized you know they were not
static and local
the the people who made the cathedrals
they were traveling
right by the connection and yeah so that
so that has to stay you know that kind
of capacity that we have
as humanity to build collective
intelligence
uh at different scales but what is not
healthy
is to have new new zealand better going
to patagonia
and destroying the whole local economy
and they're already making the best
butter in the world
right so these are two different things
so i think the neoliberal
transportation regime that is
you know that has to change again
probably not 100
so i prefer to talk about the
subsidiarity of material production
you know like i've heard i don't know if
it's true but
uh if ireland would not have any imports
then people would have uh going
right because they there's not enough i
o there's something in the air
just an example not everything is
locally available
uh but it has to be done in an
intelligent way right so what what we
so i'm pretty in agreement with what
dennis meadow
said i i read a a report from terdelia
which is a
french community land trust and they
calculated that if you 100 organic food
in france you need 12 percent of
population
doing farming as opposed to only two
percent now
yeah i mean we've got mass unemployment
and many of the
globes are disappearing so um and it's
actually
healthy for the immune system and it's
connected
to places you know not everybody
needs all all kinds of technology you
know i look at the amish
who reportedly have the most productive
agriculture in the us i don't know if
that's true but i've read that several
times
and i was looking at the bruderhof
communities and you know their
regenerative agriculture you know they
only use minimal technology
but they use technology you know so
that's that's a wrong discussion it's
not about
for or against technology it's what
technology works for us with our purpose
right and i have 100
sympathy for people saying oh we don't
want smartphones for our children we
don't need we need tv
in our community why not i mean
it's you know you judge you judge
technology from the community
level uh how have you
how have you seen this um evolve since
you
with with frank frank case you you made
this um movie
technology quite a long time ago by now
um i don't
remember exactly it was in the late 90s
yeah yeah
um so you've you've been tuned in to
the the kind of role of technology in
this for a long time yeah
and and i'm sort of still
like i don't know i can't see the future
but um
but i i'm wondering how
how could we find the both and in this
that we don't
um create like you mentioned um
bitcoin earlier and and the kind of
energy footprint of some of these
technologies in many ways all of us
like this conversation yet another piece
that we're
producing we're putting out there but
it's it's going to be stored on some
server it's going to take water and
energy to keep it there absolutely
so i think there's two drivers uh you
know of technology
and one is really capital right it's
look at the internet how it was 20 years
ago
and was what it has become that's not
the organic outgrowth
of peer-to-peer technologies because
they were taken over by big
big companies who had a different agenda
of you know selling our surplus
attention and so they
they designed facebook and twitter to
to be in a certain way um
this that's not just technology so
that's one driver for sure
but the technocolypse movie had
and another idea which is that
technology is bad religion let me
quickly explain so the idea that i have
is that transcendence is really a human
need
so it's not just belief it's really kind
of
built in that we want this we want to
transcend go
at higher levels
and so i think that when europe
abandoned
religion uh
that drive became unconscious right and
so
what the thesis of technocalypse is that
transhumanism which is really the agenda
now you know like
all these people are now the head of
research of google and they get
you know billions of dollars right for
their dreams
is an unconscious religion so there's
different ways you can say that so
omniscience omnipresence right
that's what they want they they they
want to use technology to achieve what
they think religion can't yeah and
we we spoke to a hindu scholar he had
made a map of 64 cities
you know special powers that you can do
by doing yoga
like by location and you know and he
says well that's what
technology is actually doing so they're
really taking all these things that we
used to believe
we could do by self work and they're
they putting it there outside of us in
technology
right and so transhumanism is a bad
religion
and bad because it's unconscious that it
is a religion
and so in many ways we are driven by
some people call it male
transcendentalism
um you know this kind of desire to
escape the body to escape matter
and so somehow this is
fused with capitalism as you know a
really strong
driver so my response to this is to
become conscious of it
and to move to more more conscious
value-based design
so i have a report that i published last
year called p2p accounting
for planetary survival right it's about
how can we
translate the insights of kate wayworth
and all these other people
about planetary boundaries and limited
resources
in our actual accounting systems so that
we can start judging what we do
you know based within these these limits
[Music]
now i lost my threads uh what did i want
to say with that
oh yes so one of my slides shows like
okay what do you think about blockchain
technology
okay what is for me important in
blockchain technology
is not the technology itself but it is
the capacity to think and create
distributed ledgers
shared accounting for joint ecosystems
so accounting is really how we see the
world like
the invention of writing are accounting
tablets
in sumeria and that's really the
invention of the state
you know because it was the the temples
just noting what is coming in and out of
you know the grain
that went into the temples capitalism
is double entry accounting that was
you know uh lucho pachi i believe a
franciscan monk
in the 15th century he made like a
synthesis of different
forms of accounting to create capitalist
accounting which sees the world you know
i'm one entity i look what is coming in
and what's going out
i don't want to know anything about the
ecosystem that's not my business
right it's how we see the world so that
to have a distributed ledger a shared
accounting system and which also means a
shared logistical system
means that we can start working in
ecosystems
and this is what happened in free
software we have
in an open and transparent system which
i call whole optical
the capacity to see the hole creates
stigmargi the capacity
to coordinate in a peer-to-peer fashion
looking at signals like the bees and the
ants
right you don't need a hierarchy command
you can say i'm a developer i want to do
this i look at linux oh
they don't have it yet i can do it right
imagine
once you have accounting you can look at
streams of matter
and energy and do the same i don't need
to make more shoes
because i can see that there is an
overproduction of shoes
um so yeah so that's the kind of
let me look but okay let me say just one
thing because now this was actually the
threat and i'm finished then with that
so a libertarian blockchain developer
thinks about individuals so it thinks
about smart contracts
individual to individual a commons
oriented developer
looks at groups and collaborative uh
collaboration groups so he does
ostrom contracts he looks at social
charters
a libertarian developer looks at
commodity currencies like bitcoin
you know it's based on supply and demand
a commons developer would think about
mutual credit
right so that's what i'm trying to say
and i'm done with that
so we have to think about that
technology is not something out
there that is neutral and organic we
have to think about it it's something
that we as humans design
and therefore we can design technology
for the commons and obviously a local
community will have completely different
needs you know than a
let's say a nomad collective that is
doing free software on a global scale
right
so it's not about technology that's what
i'm trying to say it's about what kind
of technology because
you know using spares spears is
technology
yeah no no absolutely but the the sense
that i had this
that we earlier were talking about how
important really axioms
are um with regard to
how the world shows up for us and even
what what you just said
that the like like the
the frame of seeing everything
within an accounting framework um like
what i
what i've noticed lately and i'm it's
it's a question i'm sitting with it's
not like i
have an answer to it fully um is
all this good work that is is looking
into resource and allocation councils
and all this kind of idea of okay we
have a limited amount of
resources they're running out fast and
we need to create a more equitable
society and
even some people are taking it into the
bioregionals
space and saying okay let's let's look
at what what can this bio region produce
and how do we share it
as a commons um all wonderful
but if we
like by going the kind of jack fresno
venus project
way of letting big data compute what's
available what's being produced with
what technology
and having some sort of premium of the
scientists how you like you always sort
of calls it just
like that we see it now with with covet
like which scientists
there's a lot of diversity in what the
perspective scientists offer us
how do we keep control over or some kind
of
participatory right of decision making
rather than control is the wrong word
and when we transfer all of this to
the big data cloud and the people who
make sense of that
that data and i'm i'm a bit concerned
that like even
even the notion of because then people
run into the second law of
thermodynamics
um and and create through that
yet again a sort of scarcity mindset um
in my mind what what that conversation
very often
that's one point we never had that
conversation where you put out that
paper
um to my mind when we talk about
thermodynamics which is a concept out of
physics
we forget that we live as biological
beings
in very different time scales than what
the
second law of thermodynamics is talking
about yes of course the second law of
thermodynamics holds
in that perspective within that
scientific framework
it's it's part of reality in that right
yeah
but for us as human beings like we
always dissed the dinosaurs for having
gone extinct um but they made it 30
million years we
haven't even scratched the surface of
that yet
and and what i'm saying is we can create
abundant
shared wealth and beauty for
ten thousands or even a million years or
two
and that means a lot like in terms of
real lived
meaning experience that that's worth it
um
and the thermal like life
life in and of itself on this planet is
a negan trophic engine if we if you look
at what life has done to planet earth
locally is to create more abundance
over time and of course eventually our
sun is gonna go supernova
explode and and will all burn and up but
in the meantime
um yeah but i i think that the question
for me is
you know what do we know what do we do
with our complex systems
right so we do have extraordinary
complex society
which generates a surplus that allows us
to have you know scientific systems
medical systems
so what i'm fearing is that out of
idealism
you know we we actually
kind of design a very
fast downward slope
that will that could cost many many many
lives
right so i'm always thinking smoo how
can we smoothen this transition
and that requires in my view taking into
account of
you know current technology and so my
effort i know it's
not perfect and there can be more you
know radical idealized
versions of this but um
if already with the current technology
we could see
you know what the limits are in our
usage
right so the kate wayworth uh donuts
right
if that would become the standard view
of our accounting system that would be
in my view
an extraordinary advance because i don't
think everybody is ready
you know to go in a bruderhof community
you see what i mean it's like
but uh not everybody is going to live in
an eco village
but the interesting thing about the
walnut is that the donut has
two circles um i mean we cannot can have
an argument of
whether the image of the donut was very
useful because it's such such an
unhealthy thing
and a donut but but the two circles
the inner circle of the socioeconomic
foundations that enable people
in place to live within planetary
boundaries
is is almost the precondition
for staying within planetary boundaries
the approach
of starting with resource and allocation
starting from the planetary
boundaries down um but
it's when you and and that's why i so
deeply appreciate your work because i
think that
the the peer-to-peer work is actually
working much more
from on the inner circle of how do we
create the conditions that appear
in place yes because you know like
holochain i wanted to say this when you
talked about
uh you know if you look at the whole
chain vision it's not
one big thing for everyone it's the
capacity of everyone to create
their own distributed ledger like their
own
you know logistical coordination
and two if they want to to share it with
others
right so that's kind of a peer-to-peer
uh aggregation
when you look at bitcoin and blockchain
it's a world computer
every transaction has to be verified by
all the other transactions in the past
which creates an exponential energy
usage right
so when you look into design you can
think differently about how to design
those
things uh but yeah do
do we want to you know
i think if we abandon digital technology
and
all that john lonnich i i think we will
we will see a
an extraordinary collapse of complex
systems and many people will die in my
view right
so maybe maybe there is no other
solution and we will get there
but i think we should try yeah we should
really try to transform what we have
uh you know as realistically as possible
uh into like a next phase right i
i kind of i agree with you but one thing
that
that has happened to me in the last year
a little bit is um
very often in my work i i
come back to this beautiful
buckminsterfuller quote
if you want to change the way people
think don't tell them what to think
um give them a tool the use of which
will change the way they think
and that was one of the
sort of design briefs that i held close
to my heart when i was writing my book i
i regard my book as a work that works
that
does that to a certain extent but if you
if you spin that thought a little bit
further then
then um all technology is such a tool
that changes the way we think
and and it has had very positive um
and very negative aspects to it uh
sometimes i mean i love all these guys
working
on developing
technology verified proof of state
change of state
concepts to to verify regeneration and
help
like build the process by which people
can create a network
yeah exactly the only the only question
that i have with this is that
if that somehow creates an in-group and
out group for those
people like most of the world's food is
still grown by peasant farmers
and they're not necessarily as digitally
literate
as we have they're not necessarily able
to access
um this technology as easily okay they
might have mobile phones and blah blah
blah but
but do we really want to like for
example
could put this together with
conversation i had with martin from
hildebrand who
from gaia amazonas who's working with
indigenous
amazonian tribes in colombia who are
trying
to live and and um become guardians or
stewards of
the forest that their expressions of
that they see themselves as expressions
of
um and the minute you bring
that culture in contact with oh we now
can pay you for keeping the amazon like
it is
and but you have to use all these this
technology
you actually maybe not even with
bad intent with good intent but you're
introducing a trojan
horse of technology that changes how
people think and actually
eradicates even more cultural diversity
and rather than celebrating it
yes i i don't know i
i think they should decide you know and
and if you look at the amish for example
right they
they have a council of elders
and first of all they look at what the
bible says because they're you know
they're based on this faith um
but the second question they ask
themselves is what is this technology
going to do to our community
right and these two criteria determine
whether or not they accept
a technology or not and i think this is
entirely legitimate
and i think different peoples will make
different decisions
about what level of technology they want
uh and i think that's good because
i i understand what you're saying but
like i can say the opposite which is
if they don't get the minimum amount of
knowledge and technology
of their enemies they're gonna be wiped
out completely
right so i don't think it's
either or it's it's basically for them
you know to the best of their knowledge
to decide you know how they're going to
defend themselves right
but the important thing is to restore
technological autonomy
you know it's technological maybe
sovereignty if you could call it that
way it's like food sovereignty right you
don't want to be dependent
on big military nationals you want to be
able to decide at the local level
you know how you're going to deal with
food food supply and
and everything right so i think that's
that's the solution it's
it's we you know we don't know what the
best solution is
uh and we need a palette you know a
french word um
like a a series of options that these
people can have
you know um
because there's probably not going to be
one uh answer
and there's going to be a certain level
of darwinistic selection when you know
some people do this and it doesn't work
all this other people will take another
solution that will turn out to be the
best one
but i mean it i completely agree that we
do need to
technology to help this this transition
and to some extent i see technology
having the potential of enabling
the implementation of the high political
ideal of subsidiarity that
so much of what we're talking about
subsidiarity is at the core of it yeah
people talk about we need more citizens
participation and people need to be more
involved in the communities
if we don't have subsidiarity we don't
we won't get that and
you won't get subsidiarity without also
a balancing of the globalized economy to
with regionalized economies so without
economic
relocalization and re-regionalization we
can't get
subsidiarity and apparently we can't get
economic regionalization
i want to make a bit the advocate of the
devil so
if i understand it well you know both
china and japan at some moment decided
to isolate themselves
from the world
[Music]
i think in japan it was called the
dokugawa period
and this is a very interesting period
because it's demons
demonstrably a regional
uh balanced society so it uses its
regional planetary boundaries in exactly
the right balance so that it could
eventually continue forever
so that's very good news because you
know we know we can do it
now they practice child death
to do this so that's not a good solution
for us they
they would basically kill babies when
there were too many of them but anyway
but so japan leave for three centuries
in this system and i think
china also from the 12th to the 15th
century or something like that right
what happened was that when the
europeans came you know
one single gun boat
was able to dominate the whole of china
you see what i'm trying to say so you
always have to
yes you can be idealistic but you live
in a world where power
is really important and technology is
part of that power
um and so that's for me a difficult
question like
you know how like do you really but
want to be totally pacifistic and have
no arms when you know that
your neighbors are not doing it right so
this is
always a big question where you where
you know how you balance these
different uh desires and so there's this
theory which i think isn't very
interesting
you probably know about it you know
multi-level selection
where it says that you know once humans
become cultural
then the evolution is actually a
competition between groups
rather than between individuals so uh
somebody with bad genes
living in a good group is more likely to
survive than somebody with good change
in a bad group
so to speak right so um
and so these people like turchin and
richard david stone would argue that
you there's a competition between peer
politics between you know kingdoms and
empires and nations
but in order to win that competition you
have to be the strongest
so the that's how we became cooperative
as a species
what i'm trying to do is kind of change
that logic is and that's what i think
what the commons do can we create
comments
that create a primary field of
cooperation
and within that primary field of
computation uh cooperation that can be
competition for example
the guild system protected every worker
but you still have good craftsmen and
bad craftsman and that's okay
right the good craftsman will get more
orders than a bad one
and that's an incentive to learn more
and to be better
but the competition was framed
into a protective cooperative system
this is fascinating i don't know are you
familiar with the word
of the work of john stewart um
[Music]
i looked at it some years ago and i
never read the whole book but uh yeah i
i think it's pretty much the same idea
yeah
he has this this wonderful sentence in
which he defines
evolution as um that the process of
evolution is a process of
diversification and subsequent
reintegration
of that diversity at higher levels of
complexity
and then the important sentences that
throughout the history of evolution that
reintegration happens through the
evolution of new forms
of collaboration um whether it's from
the
um non-nucleated cells to the nucleated
cells to multicellular organisms
to social animals there's always this
jump where suddenly
so much more is possible because that's
a peer-to-peer that's what peter pierre
is doing for me
it's it's creating this next level
collaborative infrastructure
right um but
so that i was reading um peter pagani
which i really really liked it's called
rethinking the world
and you know it basically says the same
thing as you which you have you know
complex adaptive systems with a relative
stability
but they can only change through a
chaotic transition or
bifurcation right so in his view we have
uh in capitalism first we had the
mercantile system
you know relatively stable which
collapsed
through the french revolution and
napoleonic wars
which gave the smithian capitalist
system which was
a total dominion of capital over labor
which collapsed between 1914 and 1945
which gave the welfare system which was
a social contract between capital and
labor
and that is now collapsing and
now we need a new type of contract
between humanity
and you know the web of life
uh and so that's of course the
unfortunate thing is that we have to you
know go through a certain period of
defragment
of fragmentation and chaos before we can
uh and so that means that we have to be
pessimistic and optimistic at the same
time right is that
in the short term like we can see it
before our eyes and and
what i didn't anticipate was that the
social collapse would precede
the um the climate and other collapses
so what i'm seeing today like in the us
you know
they're very close to civil war
you know maybe not everybody against
everybody but certainly
you know there's armed militias now on
both sides
and you know that can go really really
wrong uh if the elections are not
accepted by one party or another
right so the polarization
the mutual hatred is is at an
extraordinarily high level
uh and people can't talk to each other
anymore not just in the us i mean the
u.s is
it's just worse than worse there than
than yeah
but it's i mean you see it in germany
with with with the ifd
and and the um right i have it every day
you know people stop being friends with
me because i'm not against masks for
example
you know it's because i live here
everybody has masks i don't see the
problem
i you know i live with my my old
mother-in-law so i feel responsible
even you know i'm not sure it works
hundred percent but even if it works
30 percent i don't mind if it you know
if it
diminishes the risk right
but i've lost friends over it no no
because i'm i'm an agent of uh the
pandemic
of myself with a new mask that has a
major and local pattern on it yeah
on facebook and um the next day i had
five friends less
not that i care they're not yeah well i
care actually you know emotionally i
i do care but you know
you yeah and you post something i don't
know from quidet for example
bad bad you know so
we live in very difficult times and i i
think it's this is the
i've always said this like i mean in
many ways
in this role of being a synthesizer
synthesizing different perspectives and
basically
both you and i are trying to hold
strong the value of multi-perspectival
approaches to complexity exactly
equality liberty fraternity now i don't
want to choose one for the other yeah
and i don't think any value is
represented well by any
movement right so this like i'm globally
a leftist
but you know i don't agree with council
culture
and so i have sympathy for
projects that try to establish dialogue
you know between antagonistic groups
um i that's just like that and i don't
see why i don't have the right to choose
those options that's a problem the
bridge builders
always get shot at from both sides
exactly exactly
yeah yeah yeah and it wasn't that
difficult until
two years ago but now it's a lot more
difficult and 2020 is really the worst
it's um you know the
the how fast discussions get back
right so one party on another side
there's always somebody who takes
umbrage
and goes into full you know war
mode that's that's painful
and i'm not sure how you're doing for
time that like
i'm kind of there's two things that i
know that yeah we can do another 20
minutes maximum maybe and then
yeah because
in terms of experimenting with
alternative systems i think it would be
really interesting to hear you
um summarize a little bit what happened
in ecuador with flock
and what you learned from it and that's
that's one thing i would love to hear
about okay
and and then i know that you you're
doing a lot of work on urban commons
and you started some really interesting
work in
belgium there's something called the
factory or like where
where you're repurposing it yeah i'll
give you the details yeah yeah
the first project was in ecuador in 2014
where three governmental institutions
asked us to
[Music]
you know think about the role of the
commons in development
and so the way we went about it was this
idea of like
national knowledge commons uh you know
agriculture
industry learning i'll just give you one
example if you're an indigenous youth
in ecuador you have to buy like a 70
dollar
textbook and you have to because it's a
question of prestige
like uh you know they're already
second-class citizens
and if you come to the class with you
know not good clothes and an old
textbook then like
you know you feel it right so
instead we could have a a national
system of textbooks collectively
produced by teachers
in with creative commons licenses and if
anybody needs
you know the latest updates um
you just print it out you know and add
it in some
some i don't know some way that that
allows
you to do this right so instead of
paying 70 you pay 15 and you always have
the most updated version
because of course what these companies
are doing is they just change changing
three pages
right and this but they're still
producing a new
a new version and everybody feels forced
to buy them
so imagine you know this you know in
different sectors now
unfortunately um
the national government uh was very
split about this
and in the end the faction that
supported us lost
um and you know they went full
extractive
mode and then korea was kind of chased
away and
and his successor did a very neoliberal
policy
um so in that sense it wasn't a big
success but it
it went to some local places and there
was one
mayor in sigjos which is uh the largest
district
you know so we collaborated uh some of
our research team went there and
uh created the three production commons
in that you know very poor indigenous
area
um so the way i react to this you know
okay i'm not i'm a consultant but i'm
not an activist so i'm not going to
push you know this is the work you asked
us to do this is what we do
but i think the concepts once they are
explicit
they they start traveling
so you know like something like the
partner state concept
uh is now you know part of the
scientific literature you can find
hundreds of references
i'm not familiar with that partners so
the idea of a partner state
is you know so you have a common-centric
society with a productive
society you have a generative economy
and you have
a facilitating state
so it works through public commons
protocols like in bologna
they created the bologna regulation for
the care and regeneration of the urban
commons
it has been copied by 250 italian cities
it's mobilizing
one million people in italy to work on
urban commons
right so it's by creating an
institutional design that that smooths
the cooperation
between the commoners and the public
authority
and as you know ostrom said no comments
can be successful
if it doesn't have some kind of
agreement with the public authority
because otherwise the police can come in
and close you down anytime
so you know that's the reality it also
sounds like it's
it's the instrument to
make subsidiarity a reality yeah because
i mean think about
kovit 19 so you know the state and the
market were failing to produce
you know all these medical hardware
and you have a massive mobilization of
maker movements which you know came
really to the fore
but they had a lot of problems because
the the other side wasn't
ready had no processes to accept or not
accept
yeah to coordinate with good quality
yeah yeah
so then what happened was that in france
the public hospitals
around paris actually created their own
you know partner state
kind of protocol where they they
invented the system to you know check
the input and accept it
and i think this is a very important you
know institutional reform that needs to
happen in the whole world
that because the thing is in that the
old welfare model
it's the state and the market right and
the state
is a bit paternalistic so it provides
services that are consumed by citizens
right
it doesn't really allow for
co-production
uh and you know autonomy so the partner
state is a whole set of ideas
about how we can uh adapt the state form
so that it works for the
the expansion of the commons how do you
this makes me want to ask another
question
so much is being said about
multi-stakeholder integration processes
and then
you get the cross-sector like the
traditional three sectors yeah
and i i often find that maybe maybe the
the whole
thought form the organizing idea of
thinking in three sectors
actually keeps us trapped um because
they're not
exclusive circles like everybody who's
in
the public sector or the private sector
is actually also a member of the third
sector by
just being that's true and that's what
about exactly
that's one of the things that we found
in ghent is that
you know almost all the urban commons
they were supported by public
officials but
almost like unofficially right
but personally i think if it's official
and and with protocols it would
you know it would allow them to go much
faster and scale up a lot of things
right um because don't forget you have
two sides right you
you are you know you and me we can be
very uh
at home in informal processes
and do a lot of things bottom up but
then once you face these institutions
they are not like you
they want to control everything so
that's where all these compromises come
in you know you use the language
that they can understand and and live
with and work with
and so it's kind of a mutual adaptation
i i personally think it's
inevitable otherwise we don't make any
progress because otherwise you just get
like
i still believe in the state you know so
let's take an example you have
social welfare it was an invention of
the labor movement
right since the um the labor aristocracy
which had this memory of the guilds
which created these
solidarity mechanisms the social commons
and then once the labour was strong
enough the state took it over you know
beverage model and the bismarck model
um
[Music]
what we lost then was the commoning and
the autonomy but what we gained was 100
percent rights for everyone
right you you go from a situation where
only 20 percent population
is able to actually do this
to a situation where it becomes a
guaranteed right of every citizen i
think that's progress personally right
um so that's why i think the the the
good institution has as a function
something that you know represents the
common interest of all the people in
given territory
but what i'm trying to add to this story
is that we now have all these flows
and they also need to be part of the
picture
right so typically somebody like me i
leave belgium
i lose all my welfare benefits
because there's no no recognition by the
territorial
that we are now living with global
networks you know they can't
they can't see it so this is what we
need to work on is
creating hybrid adaptations where the
trans local
and the transnational can start to work
with
the territorial and they can both enrich
each other
and is that like the the recent work
that you're doing in belgium and that
now got slowed down by by the pandemic
and
is that going in that direction uh
yes and no so so i'm working with
smart.coop
[Music]
which is a very interesting outfit
because i don't know if you know much
about it but
so as a freelancer you join them
and they will do something called
factoring which normally was done
in the past by private companies
so you put two percent of your wage in a
common pot that allows them to pay you
within seven days
which is a huge thing for a freelancer
you normally have to wait
at least three months for payment on
average
and then after six months they create a
second account
and it calculates what kind of salary
you can pay yourself
right then you become an employee of the
co-op
and you are actually a salaried worker
with all the protections of the welfare
state
i think this is a brilliant hack and i
call it autonomous worker because in
this system
you're both free like you can follow
your passions
and choose your employer and choose your
project
and you are also a worker with who's
protected by
by the by the state um
so i've been working on things like
sustainable well-being
and you know so but for example this
idea i just
explained to you that's that's not not
there yet
so i wanted basically my idea was to
create a container
like the estonia e-government model
right
so i'm a belgian in thailand i can join
the container
of thailand but then it translates into
my belgian
legal system
so
it's a shift in consciousness right is
to
to know that the trans local is just as
important as the purely
territory and this is my critique on
localization
is that it's sometimes too regressive
and you know
as an absolute agreement yeah yeah
absolutely i mean it's not
because the danger um also politically
is that
as we're seeing this polarization at the
moment what's beginning to happen
is that you get two very very different
groups talking about
bioregionalism and localization right
and for very very different motives
and one of them is kind of living within
the planetary boundaries and creating
more community and
and and sees it as a movement that is in
global solidarity enabling other
bioregions to do the same
and basically refitting the human impact
on earth by a physical reality of the
region that people inhabit
that's one side and the other side is is
a kind of
and the world's going to like that
there's more diversity there or there's
a lot of diversity in that group from
ultra right-wing kind of um
protective and sometimes xenophobic
exactly localization yeah yeah this is a
big big issue
um yeah so
you know i'm also much in favor of this
kind of planetary thing right
which is like planetary guilds
uh where like you know workers could
also
organize themselves you know on a
trans national transnational right so
i'm not talking about international
because that's what most people think or
international you know wh
no no no we're talking about native
digital
you know trans local organization forms
of organization
like a guild in the middle ages where
you know the cathedral workers would
travel
it's interesting that's what i want to
see actually the the analogy to the
middle ages is actually really
interesting because in the middle ages
we didn't really we were just starting
to form
those socio-political entities that we
now call nation states
yeah and um to some extent
most of the ones that people are now so
enamored with the ones that the
political leaders like to say dot dot
dot first
are basically
structurally power over systems they're
not
power with they're not shared power
systems and
um while it's very difficult and again
it's not at both end and
there will be a long transition but my
sense is that if we want to
refit the human presence on earth
to the boundaries of a planet with a
biosphere
we can do that at the bioregional scale
where bioregions
and watersheds have a physical reality
context within which we
know how to how to a b of healing
influence like to
how to be restorers regenerators and and
and healers
to the ecosystem and the social system
and and the local economy or regional
economy
but we all we also need
the global coordination solidarity
peer-to-peer knowledge exchange i like
the way that you simplified it by saying
if it's heavy
it stays in the region it travels great
um the nation state in that game
to my mind has only one role which is to
smooth the transition
ideally yes i i fear
that in the short term that it's not
gonna happen like that so
you know a lot of people think the
nation city will disappear
i think in the short term it will
strengthen
uh it's like a natural protective
reaction right
uh a lot of you know let's call them the
na the original native
workers they feel victimized by
globalization
uh but even by migration that might be
right or wrong but that's what you know
that's what they feel
and the left has become the party of the
cognitariat you know the educated
uh urban people
so we're seeing this split right now
whereas you know the right-wing populist
is the merchant class
has convinced the working class that
they
can protect themselves as a on on a
nation-state basis
right and so i i see this happening
everywhere
[Music]
at least for a while
the problem with that is of course that
they're going to enter into very
competitive
behaviors with other nation states
and they're gonna see that it's not
working and and so
basically unfortunately i think we need
to go through these
pedagogical catastrophes before we get
something better
that just out of some kind of realism
you know i don't see the state
disappearing on the country these people
want to strengthen it
but i think fundamentally you know that
this is not a way forward
to solve a number of really serious
global ecological problems
um but you know we don't always
live in the politics that we want yeah
no it's all
work in progress and that's why and and
our lifespans are too short to really
comprehend transitions because
transitions don't
care about the fact that we only live 70
to maybe
lucky 100 years and while they can be
very fast a lot of them like we
all our lives have been in a transition
for us
it's it's only visible so you're
probably familiar with
and i think we we need to stop but just
finish maybe with this
you're probably familiar with you know
the game b group with daniel
schmuckenberg and jordan hall
and i had a conversation with daniel uh
last week
and i don't know how he comes to this
conclusion but i was really intrigued he
says you know
we need now we have one generation
to create a framework for the change in
three or four generations
that's good um it's interesting i'm i'm
still kind of saying like
i don't think we have that much time but
who knows right so i'm i didn't have the
time to explore it further but i think
that was an interesting
because you know that's why i'm looking
now as we said in the beginning i'm
looking at
those temporal rhythms uh
you know these theories of history that
it's called wave pulse theories that
look at
you know a succession of degradative
extractive
periods which lead to overuse and
collapse and then create
a postwar regenerative reaction
where the commons is the core way to
heal a society
and i i think this is where we this is
where we are at we are
since 2008 an accumulation of downward
spiral
and at the same time all these germs are
coming up because people have to
and so we're both going through the
degradation
and the regeneration at this stage at
the same time
right yeah no i i i exactly it's a both
hand we're in the middle of
course the degeneration is much bigger
than regeneration that's
that's problematic but i mean that's
just very briefly the
the adaptive cycle in in zillions theory
um i'll send you the link afterwards a
friend of mine tobias luther from the
itaha in in zurich
has um turned that into rather than
keeping it in the loop
and it turned it into what he calls
adaptive waves but with the same phases
in it
and the key bit is the to recognize that
collapse and breakdown
is actually part of the undoing of
structures that no longer serve
new alternatives to even have a chance
exactly and that's what peter pagani
says right he describes the crystal
uh you know the snow crystal
uh it has to disintegrate before it
becomes rain
it's you know there's no evolution there
it's really a breakdown
and reconstitution
well i know you're right so this has
been wonderful
and we could go on yeah thank you daniel
yeah um well
and enjoy that make the most of being
with your family
and yes it's nice not to travel for a
while i
i heard myself yeah yeah yeah yeah i
traveled so much and
and now i'm trying to make the ball the
best yeah yeah it makes you slow down
but i i do hope we we share the same
physical space again sometimes
yes i do too yeah all right okay thank
you danielle thank you
thank you bye